Vincent Price Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Vincent Price Papers1883-1992 (bulk 1932-1992)
MSS36905
Price, Vincent, 1911-1993
60,000 items 230 containers plus 8 oversize 92.5 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Actor, art collector, and supporter of the arts. Correspondence, speeches and writings, lectures, business records, family papers, scripts, programs, playbills, publicity material, photographs, and other papers documenting Price's career as an actor in the theater, motion pictures, and television, as an art collector, critic, and consultant, and as a gourmet cook.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Baldrige, Letitia.; Barrett, Edith, 1906-1977.; Browne, Coral, 1913-1991.; Collingwood, Charles.; Crawford, Joan, 1908-1977.; Dreyfuss, Henry, 1904-; Durbin, Deanna.; Guinness, Alec, 1914-2000.; Hayes, Helen, 1900-1993.; Jaffe, Sam, 1901-; Marcus, Stanley, 1905-; McDowall, Roddy.; Price, Mary Grant.; Price, Vincent, 1911-1993.; Rathbone, Perry Townsend, 1911-; Rivers, Joan.; Wickes, Mary, 1910-1995.
Organizations
Sears, Roebuck and Company.
Subjects
Actors.; Art consultants.; Art critics.; Art--Collectors and collecting.; Art.; Arts.; Cooking.; Gourmets.; Horror films.; Indian art.; Lectures and lecturing.; Motion pictures.; Theater.
Occupations
Actors.; Art collectors.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Vincent Price, actor, art collector, supporter of the arts, and author, were donated to the Library of Congress by Price between 1970 and 1992.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Sound and video recordings have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. Sheet music has been transferred to the Music Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Vincent Price Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Vincent Price are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1911, May 27 Born, St. Louis, Mo.
1933 B.A., Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1934 Teacher, Riverdale Country Day School, Riverdale, N.Y.
1934-1935 Attended Courtauld Institute of Art, University of London, London, England
1935 First professional stage appearance in Chicago, Gate Theatre, London, England
1935-1937 Appeared as Prince Albert in Victoria Regina, first on London stage, then from December 1935 to June 1937 opposite Helen Hayes on Broadway, Broadhurst Theatre, New York, N.Y.
1937-1938 Appeared in Mercury Theatre stage productions
1938 Married Edith Barrett (divorced 1948) First motion picture role in Service de Luxe
1943 Opened the Little Gallery, Beverly Hills, Calif.
1947-1950 Appeared on radio in "The Saint"
1948 Established Modern Institute of Art, Beverly Hills, Calif.
1949 Married Mary Grant (divorced 1973)
1953 Appeared in motion picture House of Wax
1953-circa 1969 Board of directors, UCLA Art Council, University of California, Los Angeles, Calif.; served as president
1956 Guest appearances on television quiz show "$64,000 Challenge"
1957-1971 Member, Indian Arts and Crafts Board, Interior Department; elected chairman, 1967
circa 1957-1971 Trustee, Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
1958 Established Vincent and Mary Price Gallery, East Los Angeles College, Los Angeles, Calif. Host television game show, "ESP"
1959 Published
I Like What I Know: A Visual Autobiography (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday. 313 pp.)
1960 Appeared in House of Usher, the first of the Edgar Allan Poe cycle of films for American International Pictures
1961 Published
The Book of Joe: About a Dog and His Man (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday. 144 pp.)
circa 1960-1963 Member, Fine Arts Committee for the White House
1962-1977 Consultant, Sears, Roebuck and Co.
1965 Published
with Mary Grant Price A Treasury of Great Recipes (N.Y.: Ampersand Press. 465 pp.)
1966-1967 Television series "If These Walls Could Speak"
1966-1970 Syndicated newspaper column on art
1971 British television series "Cooking Price-Wise"
1972 Published
The Vincent Price Treasury of American Art (Waukesha, Wis.: Country Beautiful Corp. 320 pp.)
1974 Married Coral Browne (died 1991)
1977-1982 Toured as Oscar Wilde in one-man show Diversions and Delights
1979 Television series, "Time Express," costarring with Coral Browne
1981-1989 Host of "Mystery!" series on public television
1981 Published
with Vincent Barrett Price Monsters (N.Y.: Grosset & Dunlap. 186 pp.)
1990 Last feature film role in Edward Scissorhands
1993, Oct. 25 Died, Los Angeles, Calif.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Vincent Leonard Price, Jr., (1911-1993) span the years 1883-1992, with the bulk of the items concentrated in the period 1932-1992. They document his life as an actor, art collector and critic, writer, lecturer, and gourmet cook. The interconnectedness of his activities and interests is evident in this collection. Price got his start as an actor on the London stage while he was studying art history at the University of London. Throughout his life, Price was a strong supporter of the arts and used his celebrity as an actor as a tool to bring art into people's lives. He used the money gained through acting to buy art. He lent works from his art collection and donated many of them to galleries and museums. He served on arts councils and wrote on art and cooking. He lectured on his life as an actor and on art. He narrated an academy award winning film on Chagall. He appeared as an art expert on the television quiz show "The $64,000 Challenge" and hosted a cooking show. He exploited his fame as the star of horror films to sell products ranging from credit cards to submarine sandwiches. Although Price achieved fame by playing villains, early in his career he was considered a matinee idol.
Price's papers are arranged into six series: Family Papers; General Correspondence; Sears, Roebuck and Company Files; Speeches and Writings Files; Stage, Screen and Studio Files; and a Subject File.
The Family Papers series, 1883-1992, consists of correspondence and other material grouped under the names of family members. The correspondence is arranged chronologically and consists primarily of letters received from members of Vincent Price's family: his wives, actress Edith Barrett, costume designer Mary Grant, and actress Coral Browne; his son Vincent Barrett ("Barrett"); his daughter Mary Victoria ("Toria"); his sisters Harriet Fenton ("Hat") and Laura Louise Gay ("Lollie"), as well as other relatives. Also in this series are letters from Vincent Price ("Bink") to his parents in the 1930s describing his European tour with the Yale University Glee Club, his art studies at the University of London, and his experiences in Hollywood working on his first film.
While correspondence relating to specific activities is filed by topic in the relevant series, the General Correspondence series, 1938-1992, is arranged in chronological order and documents Price's friendships and the wide variety of his interests and activities. The major portion of this series consists of letters received, although attached to much of the correspondence from the 1960s are copies of Price's handwritten responses or the responses typed by his secretary, Wawona Hartwig. This correspondence includes letters spanning fifty years from friends such as college roommate Edmund Thomas ("Ted") and Cecil Baldwin, whom he met while teaching at Riverdale Country Day School; official letters requesting appearances or proposing other activities; and mail from the public relating to his acting, writings, and art expertise. Prominent correspondents include Letitia Baldrige, Charles Collingwood, Joan Crawford, Henry Dreyfuss, Deanna Durbin, Alec Guinness, Helen Hayes, Sam Jaffe, Roddy McDowell, Stanley Marcus, Perry Rathbone, Joan Rivers, and Mary Wickes.
The Sears, Roebuck and Company series documents Price's activities as a consultant to this firm from 1962 to 1977. As part of his work with Sears, he formed Vincent Price Enterprises along with Lester Salkow and Harry Sundheim.; Mary Grant Price was also active in Sears ventures. The major focus of his work involved the Vincent Price Collection of Fine Art which Price put together as original art for sale in Sears stores. Price saw this venture as a part of his efforts to bring art to people in their daily lives. As part of this project he travelled throughout the world buying original works of art. Mary Grant Price did the framing of the art work. Shows of selected pieces were sent to Sears stores throughout the country at prices ranging from as little as twenty-five dollars to ten thousand dollars. Vincent Price made personal appearances at many of the art shows. Other activities he undertook for Sears included the development of reproductions for a decorating line called National Treasures and other merchandise such as a line of men's toiletries, chocolates, and a Bible illustrated with the works of Michelangelo. He also made public appearances and advertising commercials promoting various Sears products and ventures. Correspondence with Julius and Lessing J. Rosenwald, artists such as Streeter Blair, Peter Hurd, Harold Towne, and Andrew Wyeth, and with the major figures involved in planning and administering these Sears activities is also included.
Price's writings on a wide range of subjects are contained in the Speeches and Writings Files, 1931-1991. His books include a popular cookbook written with his wife, an autobiographical memoir of his experiences with art, a tribute to his favorite dog, a book on American art, and a discussion of monsters written with his son. The books file contains original drafts, correspondence, research notes, and clippings, with the exception of I Like What I Know, which does not contain a draft of the text. The articles file covers topics ranging from his acting career to art, travel, and cooking. Price also wrote forewords and introductions to cookbooks, art books, and biographies. The columns file relates to the newspaper column on art which Price wrote from 1966 to 1970 for the Chicago Tribune-New York News syndicate; it contains his drafts, notes, and related correspondence. The poetry file contains poems Price wrote throughout his life, many jotted on scraps of paper, the back of script pages, and airplane boarding passes. Poetry was a common form of expression for several generations of the Price family. The Family Papers series includes poems written by his father and his son. The lectures and addresses file contains the texts of talks Price gave at specific events as well as various versions of the lectures he performed on tour.
Encompassing many aspects of the entertainment business, the Stage, Screen, and Studio Files, 1935-1992, chronicle Price's career as an actor and entertainer. Price performed on the stage, in films, on radio, and on television. He served as narrator in live performances and in the studio. He made commercials for a variety of products and public service announcements for many organizations. He went on lecture tours and made numerous additional public appearances, serving as master of ceremonies at awards functions and fashion shows, as art judge and auctioneer, as celebrity chef, and as guest lecturer on cruises. He attended a great variety of functions. This series is organized according to type of activity and is then arranged either alphabetically by title of project or chronologically. Files contain scripts, programs, correspondence, clippings, and other documents.
Included in the films section of this series are files on the majority of Price's motion pictures. Although Price was renowned for his roles in horror pictures, his film career had many more dimensions. There are some gaps in coverage, primarily in films from the 1940s, including Laura, Leave Her to Heaven, and Shock. Contained in the files, however, are materials relating to his first movie, Service de Luxe; his films for American International Pictures; Theatre of Blood, the project in which he met and acted with his future wife, Coral Browne; Vincent, in which he narrated a film short by Tim Burton about a boy who idolized Vincent Price; and Disney's The Great Mouse Detective, in which he provided the voice of the villain, Professor Ratigan.
The lectures section of the Stage, Screen, and Studio Files provides a chronological record of the presentations Price conducted several months each year, such as "Three American Voices," "Dear Theo", "The Enjoyment of Great Art," and "The Villains Still Pursue Me." He lectured primarily at colleges, women's clubs, and in town lecture series. As a lecturer he often attended dinners, visited art galleries, and met with students. For a time he was the highest paid lecturer in the United States.
Price's extensive work in the theater, on the London stage, on Broadway, and in summer stock is recorded in the plays section of this series. The files primarily contain programs, correspondence, and clippings. Included is Orson Welles's; Mercury Theatre production of Shoemaker's Holiday. Price married his costar Edith Barrett. There are extensive files on the musical, Darling of the Day, which played on Broadway in 1968, and Diversions and Delights, the one-man play in which Price portrayed Oscar Wilde from 1977 to 1982.
The radio section covers much of Price's radio work, including appearances on programs in the United States and England and on voice tracks for Voice of America programs. Missing, however, are materials from early dramatic broadcasts on which Price performed, such as "Escape," "Suspense," and "The Saint."
Starting in the early days of the medium, Vincent Price made over a thousand appearances on television in all types of programming. As the television section of this series illustrates, he performed in dramas, situation comedies, variety shows, game shows, talk shows, and programs for children. He played serious roles as well as humorous characterizations of his film persona on British as well as American television. Documents contained in this section include his official statements regarding his activities on "The $64,000 Challenge" made during the quiz show scandal investigations, the transcript of Edward R. Murrow's interview with him in his art-filled home for the "Person to Person" program, and the discussion topics for his many appearances on the NBC program "The Tonight Show" from the 1960s through the 1980s.
The miscellaneous files section of the Stage, Screen, and Studio files contains general material relating to Price's career as a performer. While publicity relating to a specific project is filed with that project, the publicity file in this section contains more general and personal publicity. Similarly, contracts and correspondence from agents relating to a specific project are filed with that project, but general material from agents is filed here under business materials.
The Subject File, 1920-1992, is arranged alphabetically by topic and contains files relating to Price's personal art collection and his involvement with various organizations, museums, and academic institutions. There are files on the schools he attended in St. Louis and on Yale University and the Courtauld Institute of Art at the University of London. There are also files on his work to support and promote the art of Native Americans. Price served on the Indian Arts and Crafts Board of the Interior Department for over a decade and sponsored the Vincent Price awards in creative writing through the Institute of American Indian Arts. A few appointment books and calendars provide insight into his busy life for the years covered. In addition, under the heading "Staff" are memoranda and reports from office staff to Price to keep him apprised of news and activities relating to his projects and schedule while he was filming, on art buying trips, or on lecture tours.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in seven series:
Family Papers, 1883-1991
General Correspondence, 1938-1992
Sears, Roebuck and Company Files, 1943-1976
Speeches and Writings Files, 1931-1991
Stage, Screen, and Studio Files, 1935-1992
Subject File, 1920-1992
Oversize, 1938-1991.
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm82036905
Container List
- Family Papers, 1883-1991 (Box 1-6)
  Correspondence to and from Price arranged chronologically; writings, clippings, business papers, cards, and other memorabilia arranged alphabetically by the name of the family member to whom the material pertains.
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - June 1932-Dec. 1970, (10 folders)
    - Jan. 1971-Dec. 1988, (8 folders) (Box 2)
    - June 1989-Dec. 1991, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Other materials
    - Barrett, Edith (first wife), 1931-1941, 1958-1977, undated
    - Browne, Coral (third wife), 1973-1991, undated
    - Miscellany, 1911-1912, 1938, 1954, 1965-1967, undated
    - Price, Marguerite Willcox (mother), 1944-1946, 1969
    - Price, Mary Grant (second wife)
      - Costume design
        - "Big Fish, Little Fish," 1961
        - Costume Designers' Guild, 1963-1970, (2 folders)
        - Run Silent, Run Deep, 1957 (Box 4)
        - Separate Tables, 1957
      - Foster Parent's Plan, 1963-1970, (2 folders)
      - International Adoption Association, undated
      - Legal and financial records, 1942-1962, 1975, 1986
      - Miscellany, 1947-1952, 1963, undated
      - Personal correspondence, 1960-1970, undated, (2 folders)
      - Proposed television show, 1969-1970, undated
    - Price, Mary Victoria (daughter) (Box 5)
      - Miscellany, 1962-1984, undated
      - Schedules, 1964-1967, undated
      - School and other activities, 1965-1984, undated
    - Price, Vincent Barrett (son)
      - Miscellany, 1944, 1962-1984, undated
      - Poetry, 1961-1989, undated, (5 folders)
    - Price, Vincent Leonard (father) (Box 6)
      - Miscellany, 1912-1948, 1966-1973, undated
      - Writings, undated
    - Various relatives, 1883, 1962-1966, 1983-1986, undated
- General Correspondence, 1938-1992 (Box 6-56)
  Personal correspondence, fan mail, requests, proposals, and other correspondence of a general nature.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Apr. 1938-Dec. 1961, (7 folders) (Box 6)
  - Jan. 1962-Jan. 1963, (9 folders) (Box 7)
  - Feb.-Sept. 1963, (8 folders) See also Oversize (Box 8)
  - Oct. 1963-Apr. 1964, (9 folders) (Box 9)
  - May-Nov. 1964, (8 folders) (Box 10)
  - Dec. 1964-Mar. 1965, (7 folders) (Box 11)
  - Apr.-July 1965, (7 folders) (Box 12)
  - Aug.-Dec. 1965, (7 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1965 undated-Mar. 1966, (7 folders) (Box 14)
  - Apr.-June 1966, (6 folders) (Box 15)
  - July-Dec. 1966, (7 folders) (Box 16)
  - 1966 undated-Mar. 1967, (7 folders) (Box 17)
  - Apr.-July 1967, (7 folders) (Box 18)
  - Aug. 1967-1967 undated, (8 folders) (Box 19)
  - Jan.-June 1968, (8 folders) (Box 20)
  - July-Nov. 1968, (8 folders) (Box 21)
  - Dec. 1968-Feb. 1969, (6 folders) (Box 22)
  - Mar.-May 1969, (6 folders) (Box 23)
  - June-Oct. 1969, (7 folders) (Box 24)
  - Nov. 1969-Feb. 1970, (7 folders) (Box 25)
  - Mar.-June 1970, (8 folders) (Box 26)
  - July-Dec. 1970, (6 folders) (Box 27)
  - 1970 undated-June 1971, (7 folders) (Box 28)
  - July-Dec. 1971, (8 folders) (Box 29)
  - Jan.-Sept. 1972, (9 folders) (Box 30)
  - Oct. 1972-Jan. 1973, (7 folders) (Box 31)
  - Feb. 1973-Mar. 1974, (7 folders) (Box 32)
  - Apr. 1974-May 1975, (7 folders) (Box 33)
  - June 1975-July 1976, (9 folders) (Box 34)
  - Aug. 1976-Sept. 1977, (8 folders) (Box 35)
  - Oct. 1977-July 1978, (8 folders) (Box 36)
  - Aug. 1978-May 1979, (7 folders) (Box 37)
  - June 1979-Mar. 1980, (7 folders) (Box 38)
  - Apr. 1980-Mar. 1981, (7 folders) (Box 39)
  - Apr.-Dec. 1981, (5 folders) (Box 40)
  - 1981 undated-Sept. 1982, (6 folders) (Box 41)
  - Oct. 1982-Mar. 1983, (7 folders) (Box 42)
  - Apr.-Nov. 1983, (6 folders) (Box 43)
  - Dec. 1983-June 1984, (8 folders) (Box 44)
  - July-Dec. 1984, (6 folders) (Box 45)
  - 1984 undated-Apr. 1985, (6 folders) (Box 46)
  - May-Nov. 1985, (7 folders) (Box 47)
  - Dec. 1985-June 1986, (8 folders) (Box 48)
  - July 1986-Mar. 1987, (9 folders) (Box 49)
  - Apr. 1987-Nov. 1987, (8 folders) (Box 50)
  - Dec. 1987-July 1988, (9 folders) (Box 51)
  - Aug. 1988-Oct. 1989, (12 folders) (Box 52)
  - Nov. 1989-Dec. 1990, (12 folders) (Box 53)
  - Jan. 1991-Mar. 1992, (14 folders) (Box 54)
  - Fragments, 1972-1989, undated
  - Undated, (5 folders) (Box 55, Box 56)
- Sears, Roebuck and Company Files, 1943-1976 (Box 57-111)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, charts, critiques, planning and research notes, purchasing records, scheduling and shipping records, promotional materials, clippings, exhibit brochures and catalogs, and other printed matter.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject or name of project and therein alphabetically by topic, name of person, or type of material.
  - Correspondence (Box 57)
    - Button, J. W., 1963-1970, undated
    - Cushman, Austin T., 1962-1967
    - Loria, Jeffrey H., 1962-1969, undated, (3 folders)
    - Macht, Earl W., 1964-1968
    - Mazelow, Arnold, 1963-1969, undated
    - McNab, Allan, 1963-1967, undated
    - Odell, Douglas L., 1967-1968
    - Pearson, Charles I., 1962-1966, undated, (2 folders) (Box 58)
    - Ritch, James M., 1962-1969, undated, (3 folders)
    - Rosenwald, Julius, 1965-1969
    - Rosenwald, Lessing J., 1964-1967, undated
    - Salkow, Lester, 1962-1976, undated, (2 folders)
    - Schindler, Burton, 1964-1967, (5 folders) (Box 59)
    - Steelman, William H., 1964-1968, (2 folders)
    - Stein, Clem, Jr., 1963-1970, undated (Box 60)
    - Struthers, George H., 1963-1966, undated
    - Sundheim, Harry G., Jr., 1962-1971, undated, (5 folders)
    - Walkup, E. L., 1964-1971, undated, (5 folders) (Box 61)
    - Wood, Arthur M., 1965-1966, undated
  - Miscellaneous files
    - Directories, 1966-1967, undated
    - Headquarters, Chicago, Ill., 1962-1970, undated (Box 62)
    - National and international locations
      - International
        - Asia, 1965-1967, undated
        - Australia, 1966-1969
        - Canada, 1963-1967, undated
        - Europe, 1963-1967, undated
        - Mexico, 1963-1965
        - South America, 1963
      - United States
        - Alabama, 1965
        - Arizona, 1966
        - Arkansas, 1963
        - California, 1962-1967, undated
        - Colorado, 1962-1964, undated
        - Delaware, 1963-1968
        - District of Columbia, 1964-1966
        - Florida, 1965-1966
        - Georgia, 1965-1966
        - Hawaii, 1962-1966
        - Illinois, 1963-1971, undated
        - Indiana, 1963-1965, undated
        - Iowa, 1965-1968 (Box 63)
        - Louisiana, 1964
        - Maryland, 1966
        - Michigan, 1963-1966
        - Missouri, 1965, undated
        - Nevada, 1965
        - New Mexico, 1965-1966
        - New York, 1962-1969
        - North Carolina, 1963-1966
        - Oklahoma, 1962
        - Oregon, 1966, undated
        - Pennsylvania, 1963-1969, undated
        - Puerto Rico, 1964
        - Rhode Island, 1966
        - Tennessee, 1963-1965
        - Texas, 1962-1968, (2 folders)
        - Virginia, 1963-1964
        - Washington, 1963-1967
        - Wisconsin, 1971
  - National Treasures (Box 64)
    - Cookbooks
      - Drafts
        - Introductory materials, 1966
        - Recipes, 1966, (3 folders)
      - Illustrations, undated
      - McCauley Enterprises, 1966-1967
      - Meeting and planning materials, 1966, undated